<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.10.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://optroodt.github.io/blog/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://optroodt.github.io/blog/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2026-01-27T23:31:26+01:00</updated><id>https://optroodt.github.io/blog/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Everyday hacks</title><subtitle>An amazing website.</subtitle><author><name>Youri op &apos;t Roodt</name></author><entry><title type="html">Adding a battery to a bootleg Game Boy cartridge</title><link href="https://optroodt.github.io/blog/18-adding-a-battery-to-a-bootleg-cartridge/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Adding a battery to a bootleg Game Boy cartridge" /><published>2025-12-27T17:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2025-12-27T17:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://optroodt.github.io/blog/18-adding-a-battery-to-a-bootleg-cartridge</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://optroodt.github.io/blog/18-adding-a-battery-to-a-bootleg-cartridge/"><![CDATA[<p>In recent years I haven’t been tinkering with Game Boys or bootlegs as much as I used to, but sometimes I do some Googling to see if there’s anything cool out there. Something that didn’t exist back in 2018 was the <a href="https://www.flashcartdb.com/">FlashCartDB</a>, a Wiki that aims to gather as much information as possible on flash carts, clones and bootlegs. What caught my eye were pictures of PCB’s without a battery installed with SRAM save type, but under notes they said “After installing a battery…”. Does this mean it would be possible to add a battery later? Let’s find out!</p>

<p>I had a few days to myself after Christmas and dug out some Pokemon bootlegs. I found a <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">0883_DRV</code> type cartridge without a battery that is listed in the database! Here’s a close-up of the board.</p>

<figure class=""><a href="/blog/assets/images/2025-12/IMG_4228.jpg" class="image-popup" title="Untouched PCB
"><img src="/blog/assets/images/2025-12/IMG_4228.jpg" alt="" /></a><figcaption>
      Untouched PCB

    </figcaption></figure>

<p>I must have had the idea to do this at some point, because I had some CR2032 holders in my soldering parts bin. A quick check of my AliExpress history showed that I ordered these 8 years ago! 🤯 
The product page is no longer there, but the description read <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">10pcs CR2032 CR2025 CR2020 Battery Button Cell Holder Through Hole Case Battery Socket Connector PCB Solder Nickel Plate 3003</code>. They look something like this:</p>

<figure class=""><a href="/blog/assets/images/2025-12/cr2032-cell-battery-holder.jpg" class="image-popup" title="CR2032 battery holder
"><img src="/blog/assets/images/2025-12/cr2032-cell-battery-holder.jpg" alt="" /></a><figcaption>
      CR2032 battery holder

    </figcaption></figure>

<p>It fit nicely through the PCB and soldering was easy. Additionally, on the top left part of the PCB, you need to wipe the contacts labeled “N” and bridge the contacts that are labeled “Y”. This indicates if a battery is installed or not. Please excuse the bad picture and my dodgy soldering.</p>

<figure class=""><a href="/blog/assets/images/2025-12/IMG_4555.jpg" class="image-popup" title="Cartridge with battery holder soldered
"><img src="/blog/assets/images/2025-12/IMG_4555.jpg" alt="" /></a><figcaption>
      Cartridge with battery holder soldered

    </figcaption></figure>

<p>Since the battery holder is a through hole model, it was sticking out a bit on the back, so I trimmed those with a pair of flush cutters. I slid in a battery and reassemled the case. It’s a tight fit, but the case closes. I flashed <a href="https://modretro.com/products/tetris">Tetris® for Chromatic</a> (sorry!) to the cart and my data is now properly saved! Only time will tell how long the save data will last. 🤞</p>]]></content><author><name>Youri op &apos;t Roodt</name></author><category term="gameboy" /><category term="battery" /><category term="bootleg" /><category term="soldering" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[In recent years I haven’t been tinkering with Game Boys or bootlegs as much as I used to, but sometimes I do some Googling to see if there’s anything cool out there. Something that didn’t exist back in 2018 was the FlashCartDB, a Wiki that aims to gather as much information as possible on flash carts, clones and bootlegs. What caught my eye were pictures of PCB’s without a battery installed with SRAM save type, but under notes they said “After installing a battery…”. Does this mean it would be possible to add a battery later? Let’s find out!]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Backlighting a Game Boy Pocket with a burnt polarizer</title><link href="https://optroodt.github.io/blog/backlighting-a-game-boy-pocket-with-a-burnt-polarizer/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Backlighting a Game Boy Pocket with a burnt polarizer" /><published>2018-04-14T19:14:00+02:00</published><updated>2018-04-14T19:14:00+02:00</updated><id>https://optroodt.github.io/blog/backlighting-a-game-boy-pocket-with-a-burnt-polarizer</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://optroodt.github.io/blog/backlighting-a-game-boy-pocket-with-a-burnt-polarizer/"><![CDATA[<p>After the good experience I had with the Japanese Game Boy games from Japan 4 You I decided to pickup some cheap Game Boy Pockets. They list a lot of items as ‘not working’ or ‘read item condition’ for a low price. I’m not really interested in buying perfectly fine and new hand helds, I want to fix something, so I went for three listed as ‘not working’ and one as ‘read item condition’ but with an obvious burnt front polarizer. I paid about 70 euro for the 4 Pockets, which includes 20 euro import duties for The Netherlands. It’s not exactly cheap, but I guess it’s decent.</p>

<figure class=""><a href="/blog/assets/images/172930379961_0.jpg" class="image-popup"><img src="/blog/assets/images/172930379961_0.jpg" alt="" /></a></figure>

<p>When they came in I did a first inspection. There were some easy to spot corroded contacts. The removable contacts can easily be cleaned by dropping them in a bit of vinegar but the contacts are harder to clean. I used an old toothbrush and carefully cleaned most of it. I gave the cases a good clean in a soapy water and let them dry. I managed to get three out of four Pockets working again! I had to solder one speaker to another board and all four of the screens work. The last board just seems dead although I haven’t tried it with a power adapter yet because I don’t have one that fits.</p>

<figure class=""><a href="/blog/assets/images/172930379961_1.jpg" class="image-popup"><img src="/blog/assets/images/172930379961_1.jpg" alt="" /></a></figure>

<p>The thing I was looking forward to the most was fixing and backlighting the burnt screen. The screens have two polarizers, one attached to the front and one attached to the back together with a reflective layer. The big black circle is a sign of a burnt front polarizer. For this project I had to remove both… Removing the back polarizer is basically the same as on the DMG, but with even less space to work with. It’s really tight and you have to be very, very carefull. I had some residue left so I spent a lot of time rubbing and cleaning. The front polarizer was even worse! The burnt area leaves a thick crusty glue residue which is particularly hard to remove. I start with regular alcohol but went on to use turpentine, not sure if it was smart but it seemed to help. Also wrapping an old credit card in cleaning tissues helps scrape off everything. This whole process was really frustrating and I’m not sure if I would do it again.</p>

<p>For this backlighting project I ordered backlight panels directly from the factory in China. I was hoping to get a good deal if I bought 10 pieces, but they were not impressed. For 10 units including shipping and import duties I paid about 90 euro, which is ok, but probably not worth the hassle. If you were to order 100 pieces, the price per unit would come down considerably but I have no need for that, yet. It was fun trying to find the source and order in (mini) bulk!</p>

<figure class=""><a href="/blog/assets/images/172930379961_2.jpg" class="image-popup"><img src="/blog/assets/images/172930379961_2.jpg" alt="" /></a></figure>

<p>In my cost cutting plan I also used sheets of polarizer film that were meant for iPad and <a href="https://www.partly.nl/samsung-galaxy-s6-polarizing-film.html">Galaxy S6</a> phones, I just wanted to see if it would work. They were cheap but I had to cut them down to the correct size. They were adhesive, which can be tricky. You have to be really carefully when applying the film to not get air bubbles, get the orientation and alignment correct. I had to start over a few times!</p>

<p>When searching for the correct solder points I found quite a few different suggestions and people saying that you should use different ones. One <a href="https://synt4x.org/blog/index.php/2017/11/07/game-boy-pocket-backlight-mod/">blog</a> seemed pretty confident so that’s the one I followed.</p>

<figure class=""><a href="/blog/assets/images/172930379961_3.jpg" class="image-popup"><img src="/blog/assets/images/172930379961_3.jpg" alt="" /></a></figure>

<p>This mod was the trickiest one for me yet for many reasons. I bought ‘broken’ Game Boy Pockets from Japan, I never removed the front or back polarizer for a Game Boy Pocket, I ordered backlight panels from China and I used cheap polarizers meant for cellphones. Removing the polarizers and cleaning all the gunk was especially scary. In fact, I was so focused that I forgot to take any pictures of the process.</p>

<p>The Game Boy Pocket is really small and light, which is good when you want to carry it around but not so good for extended gaming sessions. The Pocket is powered by 2 AAA batteries which have less capacity than AA, resulting in less playing time. The viewing angle of my ‘fixed’ console is a little bit off, resulting in a less than perfect contrast. I’m thinking it has to do with the polarizer filters I used, maybe the result would be better if you only replace the back polarizer. It’s decent, but not perfect.</p>

<figure class=""><a href="/blog/assets/images/172930379961_4.jpg" class="image-popup"><img src="/blog/assets/images/172930379961_4.jpg" alt="" /></a></figure>

<p>All in all the Pocket is a really nice hand held, great for a quick game on the go, but for serious gaming I still prefer the DMG.</p>]]></content><author><name>Youri op &apos;t Roodt</name></author><category term="gbp" /><category term="backlight" /><category term="japan4you" /><category term="gameboypocket" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[After the good experience I had with the Japanese Game Boy games from Japan 4 You I decided to pickup some cheap Game Boy Pockets. They list a lot of items as ‘not working’ or ‘read item condition’ for a low price. I’m not really interested in buying perfectly fine and new hand helds, I want to fix something, so I went for three listed as ‘not working’ and one as ‘read item condition’ but with an obvious burnt front polarizer. I paid about 70 euro for the 4 Pockets, which includes 20 euro import duties for The Netherlands. It’s not exactly cheap, but I guess it’s decent.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Replacing the battery on a Game Boy cartridge</title><link href="https://optroodt.github.io/blog/replacing-the-battery-on-a-game-boy-cartridge/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Replacing the battery on a Game Boy cartridge" /><published>2018-04-14T18:18:00+02:00</published><updated>2018-04-14T18:18:00+02:00</updated><id>https://optroodt.github.io/blog/replacing-the-battery-on-a-game-boy-cartridge</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://optroodt.github.io/blog/replacing-the-battery-on-a-game-boy-cartridge/"><![CDATA[<p>I hang out in <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/Gameboy/">/r/Gameboy/</a> a lot and I see that quite a few people mention J4U or <a href="http://stores.ebay.com/JAPAN4YOU-STORE">japan_4_you</a> on eBay as their resource for buying Game Boy related stuff. They have a lot of good stuff and some things are just dirt cheap! While browsing I found Japanese releases of Gargoyles Quest ($6.50), Mole Mania ($5), Mario’s Picross ($2), Yoshi’s Cookie ($1.30), Donkey Kong Land ($3.20), Golf and Tennis ($1 each). I decided to buy the whole bunch and threw in Tamagotchi for $1 because of the white cartridge, even though I won’t be able to read anything.</p>

<figure class=""><a href="/blog/assets/images/172928918046_0.jpg" class="image-popup"><img src="/blog/assets/images/172928918046_0.jpg" alt="" /></a></figure>

<p>It took about two weeks for the cartridges to arrive. The cartridges are in decent shape, they have some discolorations, some have markings and they all play after the mandatory blowing into the cartridge 😉. Actually all but Yoshi’s Cookie, which doesn’t work in my DMG, but plays fine in a GBA, so I can’t really blame the seller.</p>

<p>During my testing of each of the carts, I found that Picross and Mole Mania wouldn’t save anymore, which shouldn’t come as a surprise as the batteries are more than 20 years old! I anticipated the batteries would be dead so I had already ordered some <a href="https://nl.aliexpress.com/item/10pcs-lot-CR1616-Button-Cell-Batteries-3V-2-Feet-Welding-Solder-Pins-50mAh-Watch-Accessories-1616/32820102240.html">CR1616</a> coin cell batteries with solder tabs from AliExpress.</p>

<figure class=""><a href="/blog/assets/images/172928918046_1.jpg" class="image-popup"><img src="/blog/assets/images/172928918046_1.jpg" alt="" /></a></figure>

<p>Did you know that the name of these batteries describe the width and height? 1616 means 16mm diameter and 1.6mm thickness. Likewise the ubiquitous CR2032 batteries are 20mm in diameter and 3.2mm in height, cool right?</p>

<p>I opened up the cartridges and desoldered the batteries. The tabs on the batteries I ordered are slightly different and instead of just rotating the battery I opted for bending the tabs and making a really ugly contact. I feel like such an idiot, but I guess we learn every day!</p>

<figure class=""><a href="/blog/assets/images/172928918046_2.jpg" class="image-popup"><img src="/blog/assets/images/172928918046_2.jpg" alt="" /></a></figure>

<figure class=""><a href="/blog/assets/images/172928918046_3.jpg" class="image-popup"><img src="/blog/assets/images/172928918046_3.jpg" alt="" /></a></figure>

<p>At least the games save again!</p>]]></content><author><name>Youri op &apos;t Roodt</name></author><category term="gameboy" /><category term="battery" /><category term="japan4you" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I hang out in /r/Gameboy/ a lot and I see that quite a few people mention J4U or japan_4_you on eBay as their resource for buying Game Boy related stuff. They have a lot of good stuff and some things are just dirt cheap! While browsing I found Japanese releases of Gargoyles Quest ($6.50), Mole Mania ($5), Mario’s Picross ($2), Yoshi’s Cookie ($1.30), Donkey Kong Land ($3.20), Golf and Tennis ($1 each). I decided to buy the whole bunch and threw in Tamagotchi for $1 because of the white cartridge, even though I won’t be able to read anything.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Reflashing multi carts</title><link href="https://optroodt.github.io/blog/reflashing-multi-carts/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Reflashing multi carts" /><published>2018-03-21T19:43:00+01:00</published><updated>2018-03-21T19:43:00+01:00</updated><id>https://optroodt.github.io/blog/reflashing-multi-carts</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://optroodt.github.io/blog/reflashing-multi-carts/"><![CDATA[<p>Previously I had only reflashed single game cartridges, but it’s also possible to flash multi carts!<br />They are being sold as 22-in-1 Pokemon carts, but the names might vary.</p>

<figure class=""><a href="/blog/assets/images/172110223406_0.jpg" class="image-popup"><img src="/blog/assets/images/172110223406_0.jpg" alt="" /></a></figure>

<p>I found that these carts need a small modification in order to work. If you don’t perform this modification, it will appear as if the Joey flashes the cart but nothing really happens. My cart was labeled SD008-6810-V3, there might be different versions out there but the procedure is likely the same.<br />You need to wipe the solder off the upper left pads and bridge the two right below it. That’s it!</p>

<figure class=""><a href="/blog/assets/images/172110223406_1.jpg" class="image-popup"><img src="/blog/assets/images/172110223406_1.jpg" alt="" /></a></figure>

<p>Now, in order to compile roms you’ll need to use BennVenn’s Multi-ROM compiler which you can find on his <a href="https://bennvenn.myshopify.com/pages/downloads">download page</a>. Don’t forget to check the ‘save?’ checkbox if your game has a save ability.</p>

<figure class=""><a href="/blog/assets/images/172110223406_2.png" class="image-popup"><img src="/blog/assets/images/172110223406_2.png" alt="" /></a></figure>

<p>After you’ve added all your roms to the list, press ‘Generate Compilation’ and the program will output multiple files. The Output.GB is only for debugging, you don’t need to flash it to your cart. Find the BennVenn 256M option in the menu and flash Output1.GB to Block1, Output2.GB to Block2 and so on. Follow the instructions, you’ll have to remove and insert the cartridge a few times.</p>

<figure class=""><a href="/blog/assets/images/172110223406_3.png" class="image-popup"><img src="/blog/assets/images/172110223406_3.png" alt="" /></a></figure>

<p>The results are pretty awesome! Running in an emulator only the menu works…</p>

<figure class=""><a href="/blog/assets/images/172110223406_4.png" class="image-popup"><img src="/blog/assets/images/172110223406_4.png" alt="" /></a></figure>

<p>But works fine on the real thing.</p>

<figure class=""><a href="/blog/assets/images/172110223406_5.jpg" class="image-popup"><img src="/blog/assets/images/172110223406_5.jpg" alt="" /></a></figure>]]></content><author><name>Youri op &apos;t Roodt</name></author><category term="gameboy" /><category term="joeyjoebags" /><category term="bennvenn" /><category term="multicart" /><category term="pokemon" /><category term="dmg" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Previously I had only reflashed single game cartridges, but it’s also possible to flash multi carts!They are being sold as 22-in-1 Pokemon carts, but the names might vary.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Game Boy Advance backlight mod</title><link href="https://optroodt.github.io/blog/game-boy-advance-backlight-mod/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Game Boy Advance backlight mod" /><published>2017-10-08T23:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2017-10-08T23:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://optroodt.github.io/blog/game-boy-advance-backlight-mod</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://optroodt.github.io/blog/game-boy-advance-backlight-mod/"><![CDATA[<p>It’s been quiet for a while, busy playing Breath of the Wild and Mario Kart 8 Deluxe on the Nintendo Switch. I still follow what’s going on in the modding scene, I watch other people’s mods and occasionally pick up some cheap handhelds. A couple of things led me to doing a Game Boy Advance backlight mod, making it possibly the best retro handheld console there is! 1) using BennVenn’s <a href="https://bennvenn.myshopify.com/products/reader-writer-gen2">JoeyJoebags</a> you can flash Chinese knockoff cartridges 2) I found a NES emulator/rom compiler for GBA, and 3) the GBA is backwards compatible with the original Game Boy and Game Boy Color games.</p>

<p>I’ll go into some more detail on each.</p>

<p>1) I initially bought the JoeyJoebags to be able to flash homebrew to cartridges and play them on real hardware, which I’ll write about later. Never did I realise that you can actually reflash the Chinese GBA Pokemon clones, and other carts too. Most likely you’ll have to patch the ROM for it to work and save properly, but that’s okay. However, if your clone cartridge does not have a backup battery things get more complicated, which I’ll get into in again another post. Let’s just assume we can flash any rom for now.</p>

<p>2) <a href="https://github.com/catskull/pocketnes">Pocketnes</a> is a great emulator that runs NES games in full speed on a GBA. It has been around for a very long time, but I never came across it as I wasn’t really into GBA consoles. It comes with an application that let’s you select your NES roms and it will compile a GBA rom that includes both the emulator and the NES roms you chose. I created a compilation of my favourite games as a kid, flashed it to a Pokemon cart and it’s absolute magic. I might write up a post specifically about Pocketnes, it’s really good.</p>

<p>3) Because of it’s compatibility with older systems you have a ton of games at your disposal. Sure, you could play GB games on a backlight modded DMG or Pocket, but what about Game Boy Color? Yes, you can mod a <a href="https://www.retromodding.com/products/bennvenns-gbc-backlight-conversion-ribbon-cable-for-ags-101-lcd?variant=40387234957">GBC using AGS-101 screen</a>, but it’s pretty expensive and it hardly fits into the shell. So why limit yourself to just GB and GBC? You could pickup a Game Boy Advance SP with a backlight, that’s the AGS-101 model, but they are also pretty expensive and I don’t really like the form factor. It’s just too small for my liking. GBA it is!</p>

<p>I picked up a couple of GBA’s on the cheap, really old and dirty ones. The one below was also missing the battery compartment lid.</p>

<figure class=""><a href="/blog/assets/images/166192026036_0.jpg" class="image-popup"><img src="/blog/assets/images/166192026036_0.jpg" alt="" /></a></figure>

<p>You can find <a href="https://nl.aliexpress.com/item/LCD-Backlight-Screen-For-GBA-Replacement-Parts-For-Nintendo-For-Game-Boy-Advance-SP-SP-For/32824956490.html?spm=a2g0s.9042311.0.0.C6Lt3L">AGS-101 replica screens for around 25 euro</a> nowadays. Depending on <a href="https://gist.github.com/grantland/8c112548b44aa87dced2">which model GBA</a> you have, you’ll also need a ribbon cable. Mine were all 40pin models, so I also ordered a couple of <a href="https://nl.aliexpress.com/item/6PCS-32Pin-40-Pin-A-B-For-GBA-Ribbon-Cable-AGS-101-Backlit-Highlit-Adapter-Screen/32717494592.html?spm=a2g0s.9042311.0.0.DTYqbO">Type B ribbon cables</a>. I also bought some <a href="https://nl.aliexpress.com/item/8pcs-Full-Housing-Shell-Case-Cover-Replacement-for-Nintendo-GBA-Gameboy-Advance-w-Sticker/32539235959.html?spm=a2g0s.9042311.0.0.DTYqbO">replacement shells</a> as you have to do some modifications and I like to keep the original shells, well, original.</p>

<p>So, here goes!</p>

<p>You have to remove some parts of the case or else the screen won’t fit or not sit straight.</p>

<figure class=""><a href="/blog/assets/images/166192026036_1.jpg" class="image-popup"><img src="/blog/assets/images/166192026036_1.jpg" alt="" /></a></figure>

<p>The screen’s ribbon cable together with the converter cable end up being quite long, so in order to fit everything you will have to fold the cable into a Z-shape. No sharp folds, just gently fold and stick it down with some tape.</p>

<figure class=""><a href="/blog/assets/images/166192026036_2.jpg" class="image-popup"><img src="/blog/assets/images/166192026036_2.jpg" alt="" /></a></figure>

<p>There is only one wire to be soldered, making it quite a convenient mod. You have to solder it to the upper left pad of DA-1.</p>

<figure class=""><a href="/blog/assets/images/166192026036_3.jpg" class="image-popup"><img src="/blog/assets/images/166192026036_3.jpg" alt="" /></a></figure>

<p>Put everyting together and give it a spin!</p>

<figure class=""><a href="/blog/assets/images/166192026036_4.jpg" class="image-popup"><img src="/blog/assets/images/166192026036_4.jpg" alt="" /></a></figure>]]></content><author><name>Youri op &apos;t Roodt</name></author><category term="gameboy" /><category term="gba" /><category term="backlight" /><category term="modding" /><category term="handheld" /><category term="console" /><category term="ags101" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[It’s been quiet for a while, busy playing Breath of the Wild and Mario Kart 8 Deluxe on the Nintendo Switch. I still follow what’s going on in the modding scene, I watch other people’s mods and occasionally pick up some cheap handhelds. A couple of things led me to doing a Game Boy Advance backlight mod, making it possibly the best retro handheld console there is! 1) using BennVenn’s JoeyJoebags you can flash Chinese knockoff cartridges 2) I found a NES emulator/rom compiler for GBA, and 3) the GBA is backwards compatible with the original Game Boy and Game Boy Color games.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Flashing Game Boy cartridges</title><link href="https://optroodt.github.io/blog/flashing-game-boy-cartridges/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Flashing Game Boy cartridges" /><published>2017-01-21T13:37:00+01:00</published><updated>2017-01-21T13:37:00+01:00</updated><id>https://optroodt.github.io/blog/flashing-game-boy-cartridges</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://optroodt.github.io/blog/flashing-game-boy-cartridges/"><![CDATA[<p>I’ve been collecting some Game Boys and games over the past year and every now and then I see a game that I’d like to have but the prices on some retro games are hard to justify. Sure, you can download a rom and play them in an emulator, but there’s no substitute for playing on real hardware. You can buy flash cards such as the <a href="http://krikzz.com/store/home/8-everdrive-gb.html">EverDrive GB</a> or the <a href="http://bennvenn.myshopify.com/collections/frontpage/products/copy-of-elcheapo-sd-flash-cart-v1-9">ElCheapo SD</a>, but they can be expensive or hard to come by. Sometimes you can find cheap reproductions, or rather knockoffs, of these games online but probably not all of them. What if you could flash these cheap knockoffs with your own roms? The brilliant BennVenn has figured out a way to do it using his <a href="http://bennvenn.myshopify.com/products/reader-writer-gen2">joey-joeybags</a> Game Boy (Advance) cart reader! It seems these readers sell like hotcakes, because they sold out most of the time, but I managed to get a hold of one and it’s really nice!<br /></p>

<figure class=""><a href="/blog/assets/images/156167193586_0.jpg" class="image-popup"><img src="/blog/assets/images/156167193586_0.jpg" alt="" /></a></figure>

<figure class=""><a href="/blog/assets/images/156167193586_1.jpg" class="image-popup"><img src="/blog/assets/images/156167193586_1.jpg" alt="" /></a></figure>

<p>It comes with a 3D printed case and has a mini-usb port to connect it to your computer. I like the decision to go with mini-usb because it’s much less fragile. This unit is built to last.<br />I had to figure out how to get the software running on a Mac, but it’s not so hard and works fine.<br />I wrote down some <a href="https://gist.github.com/optroodt/9ddf0cb3a41989d2b23e9e7af4635a6f">instructions</a> for those interested.</p>

<p>I got some Pokémon knockoffs from China and tried flashing them with a bunch of different games. Wario Land, Mega Man III, Donkey Kong, Konami Collection, they all work just fine, even the save features work. Only Mega Man V gave me a black screen after the Nintendo logo, I haven’t figured out why that happens yet.</p>

<figure class=""><a href="/blog/assets/images/156167193586_2.jpg" class="image-popup"><img src="/blog/assets/images/156167193586_2.jpg" alt="" /></a></figure>

<figure class=""><a href="/blog/assets/images/156167193586_3.jpg" class="image-popup"><img src="/blog/assets/images/156167193586_3.jpg" alt="" /></a></figure>

<p>You can use the reader to dump roms and save games from your own cartridges too.</p>

<p>Now all I have to do is write my own game!</p>

<p>So far I’m really happy with this little device. <a href="http://bennvenn.myshopify.com/">BennVenn</a> makes a lot more Game Boy related hardware, it’s really amazing to see. I highly recommend following him on <a href="https://www.facebook.com/BennVennElectronics/">Facebook</a> if your interested in this sort of stuff</p>]]></content><author><name>Youri op &apos;t Roodt</name></author><category term="joeyjoebags" /><category term="game boy" /><category term="flashcart" /><category term="bennvenn" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I’ve been collecting some Game Boys and games over the past year and every now and then I see a game that I’d like to have but the prices on some retro games are hard to justify. Sure, you can download a rom and play them in an emulator, but there’s no substitute for playing on real hardware. You can buy flash cards such as the EverDrive GB or the ElCheapo SD, but they can be expensive or hard to come by. Sometimes you can find cheap reproductions, or rather knockoffs, of these games online but probably not all of them. What if you could flash these cheap knockoffs with your own roms? The brilliant BennVenn has figured out a way to do it using his joey-joeybags Game Boy (Advance) cart reader! It seems these readers sell like hotcakes, because they sold out most of the time, but I managed to get a hold of one and it’s really nice!]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Pirate Game Boy Advance carts?</title><link href="https://optroodt.github.io/blog/pirate-game-boy-advance-carts/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Pirate Game Boy Advance carts?" /><published>2016-10-30T16:20:00+01:00</published><updated>2016-10-30T16:20:00+01:00</updated><id>https://optroodt.github.io/blog/pirate-game-boy-advance-carts</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://optroodt.github.io/blog/pirate-game-boy-advance-carts/"><![CDATA[<p>I love the Nintendo DS Lite for its form factor and it’s versatility. It plays DS games and GBA games and with an R4 or M3 card it can even run emulators for NES or GB/GBC.<br />I didn’t have any GBA games I could play so I wanted to get some. Actually I do have a few Japanese titles but they’re in… Japanese. As a kid I loved The Legend Of Zelda: A Link To The Past, it was unprecedented at the time. A vast world to explore, a great storyline, beautiful graphics and a return to form like the original The Legend Of Zelda. This version is a remake, but it looks very good and stays true to the original. At a local flea market (IJ-hallen) I recently found a copy of The Minish Cap but the seller asked 20 euro for it. I took a closer look and noticed that the Nintendo© logo on the back of the cartridge was in a strange font, not very Nintendo like. I told the seller <i>“… but it’s not an original”</i>, he said he knew and he still wanted 20 euro. Needless to say I passed on the deal.</p>

<p>I found a Chinese seller selling some of the more popular GBA games, including A Link To The Past and Super Mario Advance 4, which is actually Super Mario Bros. 3 with an extra Mario Bros. game. The games only came in a case, but no manual or anything else. They looked really good, authentic even. The strange thing was that you could specify if you wanted an EU or a USA label on your cart and you could order as many as you liked. They were going for about 6 euro each so while it smelled like piracy I decided to give it a try.</p>

<figure class=""><a href="/blog/assets/images/152513092576_0.jpg" class="image-popup"><img src="/blog/assets/images/152513092576_0.jpg" alt="" /></a></figure>

<p>A few weeks later my games arrived and I tried them out. They work fine, including saving, altough Super Mario Advance 4 has an error before the game begins, complaining about “Saved data is corrupted”. I played through most of the game in various sessions and my progress is saved, so I’m not exactly sure what’s going on here.<br /></p>

<figure class=""><a href="/blog/assets/images/152513092576_1.jpg" class="image-popup"><img src="/blog/assets/images/152513092576_1.jpg" alt="" /></a></figure>

<p>And then it works fine…</p>

<figure class=""><a href="/blog/assets/images/152513092576_2.jpg" class="image-popup"><img src="/blog/assets/images/152513092576_2.jpg" alt="" /></a></figure>

<p>I must admit, to the trained eye, it’s easy to see that these cartridges are knock-offs: The corners of the labels are much rounder than originals, the Nintendo logo is a bit dodgy and the plastic is much softer/bendy than original cartridges. However, if you’re not aware that pirate cartridges exist it’s very easy to take these cartridges for the real thing! The backs look legit. The bottom one is an official cartridge.<br /></p>

<figure class=""><a href="/blog/assets/images/152513092576_3.jpg" class="image-popup"><img src="/blog/assets/images/152513092576_3.jpg" alt="" /></a></figure>

<p>For comparison, I also opened an original copy of “Bakuten Shoot Beyblade”.</p>

<figure class=""><a href="/blog/assets/images/152513092576_4.jpg" class="image-popup"><img src="/blog/assets/images/152513092576_4.jpg" alt="" /></a></figure>

<p>Wow, it looks really interesting! The strange Nintendo logo on the PCB, the “AGB-E05-01” marking, the silver cartridge connector pins, the partially scraped off stickers on the chips… have they been salvaged from other electronics and been repurposed? There are actually people recreating cartridges of 12 year old games. Just wow, really fascinating. Obviously these cartridges don’t have the same collectible value as originals, but then again, these are a lot cheaper: an original Link To The Past for GBA fetches between 25 and 70 euro, depending on its state.<br /></p>]]></content><author><name>Youri op &apos;t Roodt</name></author><category term="gba" /><category term="pirate" /><category term="cartridges" /><category term="nintendo" /><category term="zelda" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I love the Nintendo DS Lite for its form factor and it’s versatility. It plays DS games and GBA games and with an R4 or M3 card it can even run emulators for NES or GB/GBC.I didn’t have any GBA games I could play so I wanted to get some. Actually I do have a few Japanese titles but they’re in… Japanese. As a kid I loved The Legend Of Zelda: A Link To The Past, it was unprecedented at the time. A vast world to explore, a great storyline, beautiful graphics and a return to form like the original The Legend Of Zelda. This version is a remake, but it looks very good and stays true to the original. At a local flea market (IJ-hallen) I recently found a copy of The Minish Cap but the seller asked 20 euro for it. I took a closer look and noticed that the Nintendo© logo on the back of the cartridge was in a strange font, not very Nintendo like. I told the seller “… but it’s not an original”, he said he knew and he still wanted 20 euro. Needless to say I passed on the deal.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A Game Boy orange backlight and bivert mod</title><link href="https://optroodt.github.io/blog/a-game-boy-orange-backlight-and-bivert-mod/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Game Boy orange backlight and bivert mod" /><published>2016-10-30T15:58:00+01:00</published><updated>2016-10-30T15:58:00+01:00</updated><id>https://optroodt.github.io/blog/a-game-boy-orange-backlight-and-bivert-mod</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://optroodt.github.io/blog/a-game-boy-orange-backlight-and-bivert-mod/"><![CDATA[<p>Last time I ordered backlights from <a href="http://www.deadpanrobot.co.uk/en-gb">deadpanrobot</a>, I also got an orange (or amber) one because I thought it would look cool and give a nice retro feel to an already retro console.</p>

<p>Taking off the reflective film was very easy, I think I’ve really got the hang of it now and the installation of the bivert chip went pretty smooth as well. I know where the cables should go, how to route them and the like. Everything worked as expected!</p>

<figure class=""><a href="/blog/assets/images/152512248581_0.jpg" class="image-popup"><img src="/blog/assets/images/152512248581_0.jpg" alt="" /></a></figure>

<p>However, when I started putting the case back together I noticed a piece that was a bit molten. I didn’t take the board out of the case during soldering and apparently I wasn’t paying enough attention to where my soldering iron was… Ouch! Luckily it’s invisible during game play and just visible if you look a 90 degree angle. It could have been a lot worse.<br /></p>

<figure class=""><a href="/blog/assets/images/152512248581_1.jpg" class="image-popup"><img src="/blog/assets/images/152512248581_1.jpg" alt="" /></a></figure>

<figure class=""><a href="/blog/assets/images/152512248581_2.jpg" class="image-popup"><img src="/blog/assets/images/152512248581_2.jpg" alt="" /></a></figure>

<p>Even though I like the orange hue, the backlight seems to be a lot less bright than the white ones I did before. If you’re playing in the dark it doesn’t really matter but in daylight it’s not as nice as I had hoped.</p>

<figure class=""><a href="/blog/assets/images/152512248581_3.jpg" class="image-popup"><img src="/blog/assets/images/152512248581_3.jpg" alt="" /></a></figure>

<figure class=""><a href="/blog/assets/images/152512248581_4.jpg" class="image-popup"><img src="/blog/assets/images/152512248581_4.jpg" alt="" /></a></figure>

<p>I think this will be the last Game Boy mod for a while but I had good fun, still play some Dr. Mario or Tetris from time to time!</p>]]></content><author><name>Youri op &apos;t Roodt</name></author><category term="gameboy" /><category term="modding" /><category term="backlight" /><category term="retrogaming" /><category term="retro" /><category term="bivert" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Last time I ordered backlights from deadpanrobot, I also got an orange (or amber) one because I thought it would look cool and give a nice retro feel to an already retro console.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A Game Boy Backlight + Bivert mod</title><link href="https://optroodt.github.io/blog/a-game-boy-backlight-plus-bivert-mod/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Game Boy Backlight + Bivert mod" /><published>2016-08-14T20:32:00+02:00</published><updated>2016-08-14T20:32:00+02:00</updated><id>https://optroodt.github.io/blog/a-game-boy-backlight-plus-bivert-mod</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://optroodt.github.io/blog/a-game-boy-backlight-plus-bivert-mod/"><![CDATA[<p>After backlighting a Game Boy I was really wondering how big of a difference a bivert mod would make. In pictures you see on the internet the difference is quite dramatic, but I already thought that just a backlight looked amazing… I couldn’t be more wrong.</p>

<p>First I installed a backlight, which I got from <a href="http://www.deadpanrobot.co.uk/en-gb/collections/dmg/products/backlight-kit/75777">deadpanrobot.co.uk</a>. With my previous Game Boy, removing the reflective and polarisation layer took a lot of time and left a lot of hard to clean residue. This time I tried to get the knife behind both layers on the first try and started to pull slowly. To my surprise I managed to remove the layers within five minutes or so, leaving no glue behind! Really happy it was so easy. I inserted the polarisation filter at a 90 degree angle in order to get the inverted look, which will be reverted again by the bivert chip.<br /></p>

<figure class=""><a href="/blog/assets/images/148941171821_0.jpg" class="image-popup"><img src="/blog/assets/images/148941171821_0.jpg" alt="" /></a></figure>

<p><br />I really liked the design of the <a href="https://handheldlegend.com/collections/frontpage/products/game-boy-bivert-biversion-module?variant=10270791043">bivert module</a> from Hand-Held Legend. It only requires 1 wire to be soldered (and it’s already included!), the pins you lifted (see video below) rest on the module and the other three connections are really easy to solder.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=EwymayNVFFA">Watch on YouTube</a></p>

<p>Make sure you get enough solder into the VCC, PIN1 and PIN3 holes, otherwise you won’t get a good connection. You need to route the wire in such a way that is doesn’t cover the screw hole like it does on the picture. Just make a nice “U” and route it past the solder points.<br /></p>

<figure class=""><a href="/blog/assets/images/148941171821_1.jpg" class="image-popup"><img src="/blog/assets/images/148941171821_1.jpg" alt="" /></a></figure>

<figure class=""><a href="/blog/assets/images/148941171821_2.jpg" class="image-popup"><img src="/blog/assets/images/148941171821_2.jpg" alt="" /></a></figure>

<p>After putting everything back together I turned it on and wow… what a difference! The contrast is pretty serious. The screen does look very blue after the mod, I liked the backlight only colour better (they use the same backlight module).<br /></p>

<figure class=""><a href="/blog/assets/images/148941171821_3.jpg" class="image-popup"><img src="/blog/assets/images/148941171821_3.jpg" alt="" /></a></figure>]]></content><author><name>Youri op &apos;t Roodt</name></author><category term="gameboy" /><category term="bivert" /><category term="mod" /><category term="backlight" /><category term="dmg" /><category term="handheldlegend" /><category term="deadpanrobot" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[After backlighting a Game Boy I was really wondering how big of a difference a bivert mod would make. In pictures you see on the internet the difference is quite dramatic, but I already thought that just a backlight looked amazing… I couldn’t be more wrong.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Powering a Game Boy over USB</title><link href="https://optroodt.github.io/blog/powering-a-game-boy-over-usb/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Powering a Game Boy over USB" /><published>2016-08-03T21:30:00+02:00</published><updated>2016-08-03T21:30:00+02:00</updated><id>https://optroodt.github.io/blog/powering-a-game-boy-over-usb</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://optroodt.github.io/blog/powering-a-game-boy-over-usb/"><![CDATA[<p>One of the cool things about the Game Boy is that it uses regular AA type batteries, which are ubiquitous. However, you might not always have (charged) AA batteries lying around. Nowadays you’re more likely to have a USB outlet somewhere around you.<br /></p>

<p>Since the Game Boy <a href="http://blog.gg8.se/wordpress/2009/07/22/testing-gameboy-input-voltage-ranges/">operates over quite a wide range of voltages</a>, it should be perfectly possible to power it using a USB cable, which is 5v.</p>

<figure class=""><a href="/blog/assets/images/148410734216_0.jpg" class="image-popup"><img src="/blog/assets/images/148410734216_0.jpg" alt="" /></a></figure>

<p>The DC jack needed is of the fairly standard barrel type, measuring 3.5mm on the outside and 1.35mm on the inside. It’s quite easy to find USB to these barrel type cables on <a href="http://www.aliexpress.com/popular/3.5mm-dc-plug.html">AliExpress</a>. I decided to order a few of these.</p>

<figure class=""><a href="/blog/assets/images/148410734216_1.jpg" class="image-popup"><img src="/blog/assets/images/148410734216_1.jpg" alt="" /></a></figure>

<p>It took about four weeks before they arrived. When I got them I quickly plugged one into a USB power bank and into a Game Boy only to see nothing happen… Aaargh. It could be a faulty cable, but the others gave the same result so it must be something else. The Game Boy expects the inside to be negative and the outside to be positive, but the cables are the other way around, it’s like putting the batteries in the wrong way!</p>

<p>I took one cable apart and rewired it so it would have the correct polarity. I plugged it in and it worked! It works from power banks, your computer, your iPhone charger, whatever you like.</p>

<figure class=""><a href="/blog/assets/images/148410734216_2.jpg" class="image-popup"><img src="/blog/assets/images/148410734216_2.jpg" alt="" /></a></figure>

<figure class=""><a href="/blog/assets/images/148410734216_3.jpg" class="image-popup"><img src="/blog/assets/images/148410734216_3.jpg" alt="" /></a></figure>

<p>See it in action!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=79f1cYOC8UM">Watch on YouTube</a></p>

<p>If you find cables that have the correct polarity, let me know!</p>]]></content><author><name>Youri op &apos;t Roodt</name></author><category term="gameboy" /><category term="dmg" /><category term="usb" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[One of the cool things about the Game Boy is that it uses regular AA type batteries, which are ubiquitous. However, you might not always have (charged) AA batteries lying around. Nowadays you’re more likely to have a USB outlet somewhere around you.]]></summary></entry></feed>